Okay.
Um, so it's a big day today, you know,
for me anyway. Uh, we're going to finish
seven years of,
uh, so there's 27 chapters. We're going
to wrap up chapter 26 and then we'll go
to chapter 27. Okay.
And
uh as the mayor of War knows, we're not
quite finished
with
life. And
uh
here's we're halfway through this first.
By the way,
um for $50 each, what a way to start the
day.
What are those two pictures? That's
easy. You got to raise your hand. You
got to raise your hand.
Why so slow?
Too small.
Can you zoom in?
I'll give you a clue. There's a lady
giving birth. Yeah. And
Language number 12.
Yeah, it's
Yeah, the rents are so high in Hong
Kong.
Oh, sorry.
[Music]
Okay. But
uh ki is not as good in
okay anyway
uh advanced desire is moreover the five
different heaps they are born from this
desire think then of aging and death and
their grief and cries of pain and
suffering. So he stops in the middle of
the
suffering he had done. He's been talking
about link number and last
desire 10. Okay. No nine. And then nine
is the water and the warmth that wakes
up the sanscara at link number two and
turns it into link
number 10. Okay, good. Yeah. So, uh it's
kind of I always go back to the
watermelon seed and you stick it under
the ground and you wait for three, four
wait for seven lengths until it gets
enough water and
heat which is
um desire for your body and mind.
Okay, in the wrong
way, what would that desire for your
body and mind look like? Desire for the
what would it look
like simply put?
You got to raise your
hand. Come on. And then you always get
all the money. You got to share. No, I'm
kidding. It's okay.
You got to talk. I don't know this
thing. You got to put it down your
throat.
[Music]
No. Go ahead. Just yell.
I believe in my selfexistence.
Say
it. Penish
me and attach to my parts that I think
does not exist and wine which come from
I gave you like
$90. Yeah. Which come from there on
sale. Yay.
[Applause]
and don't come from my feet. Let's say
it's always safe to
[Music]
say. Yeah. So, if you get sick, you
think you you must have caught it from
somebody else or something. Okay. And
you don't realize it's coming from how
you treat other people. Okay? Like maybe
you eat meat and then
you you plant the seeds to see your body
sick. Then you blame it on something
else. Some vi porn viruses that was
getting the blame. Okay. All right. Uh
then he says
uh say the last say
just say
that's an ancient ancient word. Knock as
you know means speech or mantra. May
means trouble. Mech means
sounds of trouble.
[Music]
Okay. Dumba means to to yell or to to
groan all the time like when Ben Kramer
wakes
[Music]
up. Okay. Not that I'm just kissing. Uh
so and uh it's really all the sadness
that we hear in the world of
people's parents die or you know they
find out they got cancer or things like
that and then they make noises different
kinds of noises okay that's that's all
called this morning I decided on a new
definition of magna which is to sit with
your friends at the dinner table and
discuss all your medical
treatments. That's how you know when
you're my age cuz you meet your friends
and you're like, "Wow, what's your
doctor
[Music]
saying? I got a good
one." We used to talk about girls and
boys.
So anyway uh in fact Mingak DBA is so
famous that uh there was it's mentioned
in the root suture of the the wheel of
life which is very short a few
pages and for $100 see I got I got a lot
of offerings
yesterday is going to tell us the name
of that sutra roughly
because there's an interesting part to
it. The first the first principle of
independence, right? The first principle
of the will of life. Okay. The first
principle of what's the first principle?
Oh, if this
happens that Yeah. If this happens that
will happen. If this starts that will
start and that's called the first
principle okay it means everything has a
cause and everything is coming from you
okay and it's called the first
principle okay uh
nice yeah that's almost enough to fly
back
to I'll try to do some
more and
I I I was very um one of the first
debate in Sugen's text. So, Sugen is
translating a very ancient
commentary by master bus which no one
has ever touched before and uh one of
the interest in
there by the way that's based Bandu
coming out of the closet as
a only guy. Okay. So, he he's known for
Abiid Dharma. He he wrote the Abi
Damakush but uh he comes out of the
closet in that book and it's oh wow to
hear him explain the 12 links with
mind is amazing but uh but there's a
debate it's an interesting debate and
and they say some people say that
uh that uh painful sounds that people
make towards the end of their life.
Okay. or when someone dies when they're
younger, those those particular sounds
should be a 13th link. Okay. And there's
an interesting uh argument about it.
Somebody says, "I think it should be an
extra link." I think there should be 13.
Okay. Some people with good morality
won't make those.
Yeah. Okay. Uh, by the way, uh, I am a
guardian and he's being cute, I think.
And, uh, so this verse uh, number eight,
it ends with and, okay, and you can see
it in the Tibetan it says D. Okay. D.
And what's happening after that? Let's
go to the next slide. You
dudes
26.9 cries of cries and unhappiness and
turmoil. All these come from
our thus it is that all this which is
nothing but a huge mountain of pain
comes to happen to us.
[Music]
There's a wonderful
uh
saliloquy by Shakespeare about these
statuses and I'm trying I have a
Shakespearean actor in the on the campus
today. I'm trying to get them to read
it. If they don't read it, I'll have
Vancouver doing some other Okay. All
right. Okay. And unhappiness
Now, so he's on verse
9 out of 12 and he he's finished with
the 12 links writes the game. No.
No. Why? You talk about the stopping.
Yeah. Anytime you teach the wheel of
life, you have to
go and then you got to
go, you got to teach people how to turn
it backwards. 12 11 10. By the way,
unfortunately, it's not 12 11 10 9.
Okay, this way we call it lung, which
means the way it starts is 1 2 3 4. It's
like a clock. It ends again. Does it go
counterclockwise?
No, it goes stop one, number two will
stop. Stop two, number three will stop.
Stop three, number four will stop. So we
focus on stopping
number one which is simply studying the
parent.
Okay. So don't blame me for teaching how
many
times three teaches
us three
[Music]
three. Okay. Uh so
anyway, he's got three verses left and
he's going to talk about how to shut
down, how to shut down the wheel of
life. I took the time to take out the
verses. I gave you the
Sanskrit. I gave you the Sanskrit in in
diiocritics which means technical
pronunciation. And then I gave it to you
in American pronunciation if you want to
do it in American
pronunciation. Okay. So that's the
second thing that you've got. So I
think people say, "Oh, I want to learn
Sansin or I want to learn Tibetan." The
way you start is you memorize something.
Okay? And you say it over and over
again. Okay? And if you want to memorize
something, memorize these 12 verses.
It's very, very, very famous. The
greatest Sanskrit ever written in my
opinion. Okay. Uh or or you can memorize
in English if you want. Okay. But it's
it's good to have it running around in
your mind. Okay. It's a it's a very
heavy good karma. It's heavy seed pl.
Okay. You're you're flying home and your
plane starts
going and you're
[Music]
like then that's the last thing
you're good way to die. Okay. All right.
So, we're gonna go to lung and say l
do means how do you shut it down? How do
you shut down your
machine? And here we go.
It's
[Music]
got
Yeah. Yeah.
I think it's I mean it's kind of silly
but the root what's the word for root
here in the Sanskrit
mulan which proves that money is the
root of all
evil. Okay. Anyway, uh the root of the
cycle of pain is doing things. Thus it
is that the wise do
nothing as so there's a lot of wise
people I've met in my life.
As such those who are not wise take
action but not the wise for they have
seen the way of things. Okay. Arguing
gaja tends
to make outrageous statements to try to
wake people up. Okay. So the root of the
cycle of pain is doing things right. Uh
how what is that in the in the Tibetan
duche? Okay, I could have written
sarization or something. Uh but that's
not what Najio wanted. He wanted
something striking and he likes to write
something you know that people will say
what he rid of all your pain is doing
things and he's responsible for a lot of
bad behavior later in Buddhism two thou
18 centuries of bad behavior people say
uh the sent people like Buakur
said the guardian said the root of the
cycle of pain is doing things.
Therefore, I should lay in my room and
watch the
internet. Okay. I don't like this thing
of putting your electronics in me
and so
this doing and people do
and then I don't know there's been
terrible
terrible misunderstandings of the garden
over history because he must have known
it would happen.
I don't know. It's kind of mean. He He
doesn't want to say too much. So
sometimes I think he says too little. I
mean I like his style. I prefer his
style. But still it has led to a lot of
people staring at walls and you know
stuff like that. People misunderstood
for many centuries.
And we're so lucky to be in a true
lineage where they don't say just lay
down and don't think about anything.
This is empty. You know, we're so so so
lucky. You have no idea how lucky you
are. You're swimming in a lineage and
you don't know you're
there. There are so for every lineage
like this, there's a 100 lineages that
say just relax. Don't do anything. You
don't think about anything. I still at
the age of 70s something I still have
people come up to me and try to convince
me I should do
nothing. Oh, regarding this I'm like
yeah
interesting. And almost every day it's
kind of weird. I have this
karma. Here's what the guardian really
said. I'm like oh really you should do
that.
Okay. The wise
don't take action because they have seen
the way of things. The word for taking
action is uh in in the in the Tibetan is
due
d which is the word for the sansscara
which is the word for fresh car. Okay.
And it means put things together to put
things together. DJ
So he's using that as a verb here. Put
things together. They don't start
things. They don't get things going.
They don't do stuff. Meaning,
for example, they might not yell at a
person who is irritating to them because
yeah, they know it's coming from. I
mean, if they yell at somebody, they go
in the bathroom and they yell in the
mirror. Okay. That's the only person to
yell at. Okay? So they don't do cha they
don't
sunsc this this person is themselves.
They know that where the trouble's
coming from is themselves. In
theory, if human beings were super
smart and you taught them the pen one
time,
uh they would never get upset again ever
in their life, in their whole life. And
I had this famous incident in a
Southeast Asian country that starts with
sing and ends with poor.
Uh, and this guy says he I don't know.
He's so cute. He says, "By the way, he
was from France." And the Singaporeans
said, "Look, he's not from
Singapore." Yeah. Yeah.
Every time you come to Singapore, you
know, you teach a stupid painting again
and again, you know, I so irritating and
I pay extra money to come to your talk
every year and why I
pay why you keep teaching the penny. I
said, you just prove you didn't
[Music]
understand. But he was a little bit
I'm not making fun of Paris. I'll go
anywhere. John Brady goes and doesn't
invite
me. John, right? Admit
it. Like last
week. Uh, I said, "Tell me honestly,
Doug, were you having an AOL finance
meeting or were you eating crepes on the
corner?" And he's
[Music]
like, "I
have Okay, next picture 11."
What's the picture
[Music]
for $0? What's he pointing to?
Wood. Yeah, I'm good. Okay, good.
Uh, by the way, all these uh, as I
mentioned, all these illustrations are
from a a wood box of the wheel of life.
It's like this big.
And uh some refugee walked out of the
Himalayas in
1973 and I was uh freezing in a
little stone hut and he walked up to my
door and he said, "Do you want to buy
this?" And I'm like, "Yeah, okay." And
uh it's
priceless. And uh so I gave it to my
stepmom and she passed away recently.
So, she left it back to me. She gave it
back to me and
uh I'm thinking of some way to fund
raise with
it, but I'll let you know. Okay.
Probably for YSI. They're always They
always need money cuz her husband is in
Paris. Okay. Uh
uh just
kidding. Okay. Here's the here's number
11. If you can stop
misunderstanding, doing things won't
happen
either. Stop your misunderstanding is to
meditate with knowledge on suchness.
Okay? And suchness just means
emptiness. And that's our thing. Okay?
I'm going to teach you how to teach
emptiness. You've probably heard it
before. I don't
care. Right? And by the way, every one
of you should teach. Okay, today is the
last
day of seven years of negro wisdom. And
maybe you didn't come to every class.
That's okay. And did I cover every
verse? No, because that would take 70
years.
uh but you have sat through some of
negular and uh in this
tradition it's therefore your
responsibility to pass it on to somebody
else. It's like
co
okay all right it's your resp once you
hear it it's your responsibility to pass
it on to some okay and that's the deal
you make that's the mazal you make when
you come into this class by sitting in
this
class it's a unspoken promise that you
will explain to another person or other
people us as much as you understand.
Okay? And they there's always that small
print in the
contract. As much as you understand okay
like if they say explain the guard to
somebody else you're
like and then they say explain as much
as you understand. Oh that I can do you
know that I can do you know. Okay. So
just just remember this verse. Okay. How
to stop your
misunderstanding is to meditate with
knowing on suchness. Such when you get
to suchness, here's what you're going to
do. Everybody raise your left hand.
Point your
finger.
Now point to something in this room
which is not coming from you. And then
you come on, you got to be dramatic, you
know.
At the end you have to
what? What's the final
mudra?
Okay. Okay. All right. And
that's that's called tatva. Suchness.
That's
suchness, right? That's suchness. Okay.
And and it's pure and it's absolutely
correct. And it's better than 10,000
explanations that have been given in
this world. That's it's absolutely
correct. Okay. It's absolutely correct.
So who is there to be who is there to be
upset at in your
life? By the way, there's a special
blessing of nagna. When you reach the
end and they give you the mudra, you
know the special
mudra. Then on the way home to where you
live, you will get really upset at
somebody. It's a blessing. There's some
kind of blessing. Okay. Probably in the
gas station or the airport or on the
plane, you'll be next to this irritating
lady, you
know, you go
like, you know, and then she'll
go and you mean, ah, that's Diamond Way.
Okay, understand? We hired
her. There's a thing in at Diamond
Mountain. There's an old thing. I don't
know if you remember it's called central
casting. Central casting is the office
where the movie people hire
actors and u so there's a karma central
casting and um in fact right now she's
getting on the plane
somewhere and she's going to connect to
your
plane and we work so hard to get her in
the seat next to
you. Then she's gonna like bother you,
you know, and then your neg is gonna fly
out the
window. Goodbye,
Near.
Okay. Okay. And and diamond way. If you
want to know what's diamond, everybody's
asking me, "Please teach diamond way."
I'm I'm teaching diamond way.
She is not a normal person. She was sent
from central cast. Okay, got it. What do
you think these books survive for 2,000
years? Do you think a book can survive
with 2,000 years if it doesn't work for
anybody? Do you think people will keep
passing it on and printing it and
carving it and translating it if it
doesn't work for anybody? And if it did
work for anybody, where are all these
people? They're on the seat next
year. Okay, I'm not kidding. That's
diamond way. You want diamond way? I
just gave you the whole initiation.
Boom.
Empowerment. Okay. All
right.
Okay. It's only the thickheaded ones
that you have to teach for seven years.
Diamond way. Some people you can do it
in seven minutes.
Okay. All right. Next. I think we're on
the last verse.
12. Yeah. There you go. When you put a
stop to any particular one, then that
other particular one will never
happen. This is how we put a perfect end
to what is a pure mountain of pain. And
the guarda likes those cute expressions.
You know, you can put a perfect end to
the pure mountain of pig. Okay? And uh
it means each successive link. Stop link
number one. Link number two stops. Stop
link number two. Link number three.
Stop. Stop. Link number three. Then you
get up to 12
and no death, no birth.
That's why some lower schools thought
you
disappear. That's why they thought
Nirvana was disappearing because you
stop birth and death. Okay. But it means
suffering birth and death. It doesn't
mean you have to disappear. Okay. Then
you stop 13. What's
that? No more crying. No more whining. I
met this lady on the plane. She's so
goddamn. Then if you stop 12, you stop
13. Okay? You stop the 13 that was never
there.
Okay? Okay. Uh now you should give
yourselves a hand because you finished
all your neg 12
[Applause]
weeks. You finished the 12 months. Okay.
You finished chapter 26.
and you're ready to go to the final
chapter. Okay, f chapter 27. Now, some
about chapter 27, which is cool.
Uh, so I was reading chapter 27 and I
was working hard on it and then I had a
satonyi which is similar to
sakura because sakura never happens,
right?
I'm asking Edmond. He's You're supposed
to If you don't make Sakura happen this
year, I'm firing you. Okay.
Uh we paid all this money to take my uh
stepson to my godson to to Kyoto to see
the cherry blossoms open and they were
late and uh they opened on the last day
on the way to the
airport and and the Chinese friends uh
said Gisha we're going to do a
play we're gonna do a play on the last
day and I said okay you know then they
did this play and they They dance across
the the stage and they
[Music]
goep. They're supposed to go like this.
You see like the the cherry blossom
opening and then they're
like it's really
cute. That's why they're coming in.
Yeah. I got to take the other the other
stepson found out. Now he wants to go.
So, I'm bringing him. Okay. All
right. Okay. So,
uh I was working on the last
chapter and strangely and you know we
mentioned it at the beginning of this
week. We said the last chapter is called
an examination paricha
of viewpoints. Okay. Like what a way to
end a book. He should say and you should
be nirvana as the last chapter. Why the
last chapter we're supposed to examine
viewpoints? It sounds like something you
should do in the third chapter or
something. It's kind of
irritating and it's long dish. It's kind
of long. Okay. And
uh often times scriptural scholars will
say if the last chapter's too long and
kind of dry like
yoga, they'll say somebody added this on
600 years later, you know, some stupid
had added a chapter. So it's tempting to
think like that because that real life
chapter ends.
So, you know, it ends very sweetly and
it should be the end of the book. And
then he's like, "Let's talk about
viewpoints." And you're like, "What? Why
you want to talk about viewpoints?"
Like, you finished your book. And then I
I was reading it and uh there's a famous
how many viewpoints?
64 in in the ancient citrus. Very very
ancient citrus. I have a
friend who for seven or eight years
translated a book called Sedanta
uh which means uh the different
viewpoints of different schools in the
last two and a half thousand years. And
he worked and worked and worked and we
found more schools, more schools, more
schools. We found different references
and it added up when at the end when we
were ready to publish the book we added
up all the viewpoints it was
101 which is such a sexy number in in
the in the western countries you know
it's like ba ba
ba in uh in China it's just a good
number
101 it's like domations and stuff like
that uh So, it was very, very cool. And
uh that's Ben's book. You should give
him a
[Applause]
hand. And the people publishing it are
after 101 years, they're going to put it
out. Is it out? It's kind of out. Okay.
We're working on it. It's done. It's
almost out. Is it out? It's out. Oh,
sorry. The ebook's out for a year. Okay.
So 101 uh viewpoints and what happened
was um every
year uh I'm responsible to write a new
DCI level and um I promised 12 levels
and then we finished and everybody's
like and I'm
like and then okay let's do 12 advanced
levels. So, we started another 12 levels
and then every year I'm like, "Oh my
god, there's another." That's what
happened to my
hair. There's another level. I don't
know. You know, and uh so I was nowadays
what I do is I see which book finished
the translation and then I create a
level from from that book. and
um and and we created uh advanced level
three last year of uh DCI directly from
Ben's book and uh it's an amazing level.
It's um it's miraculous and it's
completely different from
everything and uh I was really really
happy with it and um and I I'm I won't
go into it much but it's
examination of your belief systems okay
which in which the guardian calls
viewpoints you see what I mean so for me
Uh and by the way DCI is not religious
non-religious. So when we take ideas out
of a Buddhist book we have to also
unbutify
them and you know so you know viewpoint
became belief system and you know we
have to do this game. So you know I I
call
it the whole thing was called belief
system. examining your belief system.
And I think the sexy thing about that
level uh advanced level three is that we
did not draw a conclusion. We did not
give you the answer to the puzzle. We
said, "Here's the puzzle. Good luck."
You know, and I think that's really
cool. And we never there's no ending to
that manual. The manual
says, the manual teaches you to
examine how you view the the world and
it doesn't tell you what to do with
that. Okay? If by the way, if you can't
figure out what to do with that, you
know, you're stupid anyway. Okay? All
right. It's just like, wow. You know,
put your hand up, point your finger,
point to something that's not coming
from you. Now you met an on the
plane. What are you going to do? You
decide, you know, because that person
was
created in the past when you didn't
understand this thing. So, we're not
going to tell you what to do, but maybe
you can figure it out. you know, maybe
go to the toilet on the plane and look
in the mirror and
say, okay, when the
ladies, you know, bumping you, okay, so
uh so what we did, I think it's a very
very beautiful level. Uh if you
haven't studied it, you can ask Jasmine
or other organizers here. Tina Lou is
here. Who else is here? Yeah, they can
teach it to you. Uh they taught it for a
whole year and
uh it's amazing. And then uh what I
realized Ben was that I believe
negatina's last chapter is the source of
that examination of different schools.
By the way, we talked already about how
Shenzhen
uh walked to India through India for 17
years and found Arya Nagaja's library in
South India which was by that time 400
years old. You know, Nagaraja was long
gone maybe. And uh so, you know, he's
the original John Brady.
uh collecting all the books and he was a
book collector that's why he had the
Arjuna the
Nagas right so
uh not only was he a book collector uh
he I I believe he was a pioneer of this
idea of trying to get people to
self-medicate medicate yourself give
yourself your own medicine by examining
your own viewpoints. I'm not going to
tell you the punchline. I'm not going to
tell you the answer. I'll give you all
the questions and then you figure it
out. Okay? So, the last chapter in my
opinion is Ben's book in the way that
Iogynous Library was
all. See what I mean? And who knows
who's John
Brady. Okay.
When you
have naga snake cobra rubbing your head
all the
time, it's a
sign. Don't tell Jamie.
Okay. Okay. So anyway,
um when I when I when I looked at the
last chapter, I thought this is exactly
what we did in
AL3 and uh AL3 we condensed all of the
sedanta and we condensed all of neg
chapter into nine
questions. Okay, into nine questions. So
the the advanced level three of
DCI basically is how to ask
yourself nine different questions. Okay?
And we don't give you the answer. We
just give you the questions and then
that's supposed
to selfans answer. You know, by
examining your own answers to nine
questions, you're supposed to learn more
about
yourself and and how you think about
things. And
then normally in that process, you will
uh you
will find out some thing, you will
identify some problems with the way you
see things, you know. So, we're not
trying to we don't take a we don't go
bang on a person's door and say, "I want
to talk to you about this paper I have
and can I come in your kitchen and by
that time they're already halfway in
your kitchen and you know and and they
say you should believe this, you know,
and we used to have two guys who came to
the Mongolian temple like once a month,
you know, and uh to convince my teacher
to be a Christian, you know, which is
with an old gay hara is not a very good
idea and he's like
yeah what
about and
and then uh by the way my wife's a
Christian and it's a very very beautiful
and there's many many levels and it's
very very fantastic and I think there's
a place where they meet uh but anyway uh
there what you Instead of telling people
what they should
believe, you just ask them what do you
believe? And then when they give the
answers, by giving the answers they they
learn something. Okay? They learn
something. I'll give you an example.
Okay? So I went straight from Princeton.
I got honors. I was awarded honors. I
proved it to group Kum
Laudi. when we went to Princeton, I
showed them the thing. Uh, and then uh
then I I packed up. I didn't go to
graduation. I I I couldn't I had to
work. And uh then the next day I pack
up, I went to stay with my teacher and I
didn't know it's going to be 25 years
there. But I I was pretty sure I was a
smart guy because Princeton University
certified it, you know, and I'm like,
I'm going to come and learn Buddhism
with you. You're so
lucky. And uh so I start, you know, I
start and he he he he
didn't he who taught me every day. I was
basically the only student who lived
with him. He kicked out everybody else.
He was tough. And anyway, so he taught
me every day, sometimes four or five
hours in many many 12 years. And he he
taught me and taught me, you know, and
and then uh it was frustrating because
the only thing he didn't know was
English. Uh and by the way, you had a
translator.
Yeah, English. They had a translator who
translate his English into
English. And uh so anyway, he taught me
and it was very very frustrating cuz he
never asked me anything and he never
needed me to explain anything. So here I
am. I spent all these years getting
smart and he's not interested in my
opinion at
all and he's always telling me ah that's
so stupid you know I can't believe you
think like that you know and then
finally one day he says what about this
sba sba stuff which is the new
translation in Tibetan for
scientist he what about this science
stuff and and I said, "Well, you know,
and I'm I'm waiting for him, you know,
he's a debater. He's the best debater.
He got number one out of 5,000 marks,
you know." I'm like, "Yeah, yeah,
science. What about this science thing?
It's it's a thing." And he's like, "Gee,
I wish someone could explain it to me."
And I'm like, "What?" And he said, "You
know, we don't have that in the
Himalayas. We we don't know about
science and but you got these airplanes
made out of metal flying around the sky.
We never did that, you know. No Gishi
ever did that. That was pretty cool. And
and he said, "Can you explain science to
me?" And I'm like, "Finally, he's asking
me something this after a year or
something, you know, and and I'm so
happy that he's asking me to explain
something to So I'm
like
okay science you know it's a whole way
of thinking you know and he's like
what's what's the way of thinking I said
you know everything can be figured out
the whole universe we can figure out the
whole universe from what do you call it
uh big thing mega
things
Yeah, galactic level stuff down
[Music]
to tiny little stuff and then we compare
them, you know, quantum physics and
gravitational
theory. Two two world, two realities
facing each other, you know, quantum
physics on the tiny level and
gravitational theory on the massive
level. And then they they mirror each
other, you know, and I start telling him
all this science stuff. He's like, M you
know and then he says well what's the
one main principle of science what would
you say is the main principle of science
I said the main principle of science is
that everything has a cause you know and
you just have to
investigate and be patient and it's
called the scientific method 14 steps of
how to do an experiment and we don't sit
there in a room and say, "Oh, maybe this
is how the world happened." We we take
14 clear steps. And they it's uh what do
you call it?
Peerreed. Your peer scientists check
everything you say. All the papers you
write are checked by other people and
then they all come to an agreement about
what caused something to happen. You
know, and it's scientific method. 14
steps. You know, that's how we make
metal fly in the sky. It's like amazing.
You know, if I was older, I'd know he
was setting me up. Uh because those big
gushes are like, "Oh,
really?" And uh so I'm like, "Yeah." And
he says, "So everything has a cause.
Every every cause can be can be
explored. every cause can be found out.
That's science. I said, "Dad, you got
it. You really got it." You know, he
said,
"Wow." Then he
goes, "How did it all start? You know,
what was the first one?" You know, I
said, "Oh, that's called the big bang."
You know, we got this Hubble telescope
up there. It looks back. It sees light
arriving from the beginning of the
universe, you know, and then we
coordinate it back. What do you call
it? We figure out from the angles of the
dust moving where it must have started,
where the explosion was. You know, we go
backwards from the angles and we can
even pinpoint in the galaxy where where
it all started. you know, it's a big
bang. All this stuff just flew out and
you and me are just parts of the big
bang, you know, and he's like, "Wow,
that's amazing." You know, a whole
theory that you can always find the
cause of something. Everything has a
cause and you just work it out with the
scientific method, 14 steps, and then
you you come to the conclusion of of how
things started. And he said, "That's
amazing, Hunter." I said, "Yeah." And he
said, "Well, what what caused the Big
Bang?" I'm
like, "I'm getting uncomfortable."
That's when you first realize they're
setting you up. You're
like, "He set me up." And I said, "Well,
the Big Bang, you know, that was before
everything." Uh, you know, the Big Bang
didn't have any costs. And then he he
goes like this. This is when Ages got
you, right?
It's like,
oh, this definition of science is that
everything has a cause except
everything. And then I'm like, you
didn't really want me to teach
you. Okay, got it. So what we're going
to do in the 27th and final chapter of
Arya
Nagardana, we're not going to tell you
what to think. He says examination
parika you know sorry viewpoint parika
we will just examine what your
viewpoints are by asking you questions
about your viewpoints. Then you draw
your own
conclusions. Okay. Oh, everything's the
big bang. Yeah. Everything has a cost.
Yeah. Accept
everything. Okay. So, the point is uh
we're going to emulate
uh
Arinda's method of asking questions. And
we're going to ask you nine questions.
Okay? In in the examination of
viewpoints, we're going to ask you nine
questions about your viewpoint. And then
we're going to say, "Go to the airport,
meet your lady, see you later." Okay?
Got it? No answers. No answers. You come
to your answers that you arrive at
yourself are the answers that you
remember. Okay? Not the answers that
someone else tells you. Okay? Uh that's
all we got. Three minutes, right? Am I
Am I right, Tim?
Huh? 20 minutes. We can do
uh I
say I say we do Q&A. Okay. And then I'd
rather do the viewpoints.
No, I better start. Okay. Otherwise, I
may not finish. Right. He has to sing
3,000
people. Okay. We're going to do the
viewpoints. If I finish the viewpoints
early,
I'll do the questions. All right. So,
Francisco, we should give Francisco Gina
and Mike and all those
guys. Marina Marina.
[Applause]
It's really, really, really important to
have a good tech crew. As you know,
since we're so much of it's online and
stuff. If the tech crew is not first
class, then there's always stuff
breaking down and people don't get
broadcast and I have to stop and then I
lose my train of thought. And so, it's
it's really nice to have
a really excellent tech team because
then I can just flow. Okay. I appreciate
it. I really appreciate it.
Uh there's an there's an idiom by the
way. Idom means idea image. There's an
idiom from the earlier classes that I
didn't get to and it applies here. Tada
39. Yeah. For once, the AI did a good
job. It you get the feeling, right? like
uh you could
follow. And
in an earlier section that we covered,
he discusses the idea of ta. Say ta ta.
Okay. Now say
t t.
Okay. One you kind of breathe, right? T.
And then one you don't breathe. T. Okay.
And uh they're connected. Okay. very
subtly. So
ta ta means the edge of a cliff. Ta
means the edge or the line that
separates things. Okay. My my holy
llama's name
was
okay. And tar means go to the edge
tart. So he was touched. Okay. He went
to the
edge at the good edge. Okay. All right.
And then there's a bad t. Okay. And
that's where you uh you see things the
wrong way. You see things uh in an
extreme way. For example, you might
think that uh the
irritating person on the plane is coming
from them. Then we say ta you fell off
the cliff. Okay. But my teacher's name
it chin means gone like it in
parameita and tar chin
means reach the goal. Okay. Reach the
limit.
So so anyway uh there's two kinds of ta.
You see one one's a good t. If you get
there you're done.
probably just eat pastry cinnamon rolls
for your whole life after that. And then
the other ta is a bad thing. It's a
mistake. It's a way of seeing the world
which is extreme. You go to an extreme.
Oh, this irritating lady, you know,
probably she didn't have a good mom who
taught her how to sit in a chair in in
the airplane. Okay. And that's another
kind of ta where you
uh you go too far and you say she's
coming from her own side. Okay. And then
um into in Tibetan language by the way
uh I'm kind of a linguist. I'm not a
great linguist but I studied many
languages and and uh Tibetan doesn't fit
into anything.
there's no connection to any other
language and there's a tradition in
Tibet that their language fell out of
the
sky
and I don't know linguistically it seems
to make sense it it's not connected to
anything it's
completely unique in the in the
world and this uh word so but if you if
you breathe into a sound or you don't
breathe into a sound that sound has a
connection. Okay? Like uh ta and ta. Say
ta and ta. So t means an edge. Like this
is the ta of the table. And my teacher's
name was went past the ta. And this is
called ta also. This kind of uh there's
many uh tas which are going too far and
falling off the edge of the cliff. And I
believe
linguistically it's related to
ta which means how do you view the
world? Okay. Say tawa. How do you view
the world? Okay. And I believe
linguistically it means how do you draw
your lines? How do you draw your lines?
This is real. This is not real. This is
true. This is not true. And in Tibetan
that's all tawa where you draw
the okay so tawa means where do you draw
the ta and I think they are connected
okay linguistically I think they're
connected
uh
viewpoints studying people's viewpoints
is to study where do you draw the lines
you know where do you draw the lines how
do you define something you see what I
Okay. So remember
this t can be a good thing in Tibetan
and it can be a very bad thing in
Tibetan. So we're going to explore t
without going off the t and we're going
to tar chin without t
p. Okay. We're not going to fall off the
cliff. We're going to explore where's
the edge of our world. Where's the edge
of your world? Okay. And then I don't
tell you where to go. I just say where's
the edges of your world? And then and
then you will know yourself without me
saying anything. You will know where to
go. Okay. And that's
the very famous nega approach as a
teacher. You know, he lets you explore.
He teaches you to explore and then he
lets you find out your own discoveries.
I think it's a beautiful way to teach.
You know, he doesn't tell you
everything. In fact, he doesn't tell you
anything. He just asks you questions
about what do you think and then you you
you answer your own questions. And I
think it's a beautiful way to teach. It
takes a little preparation. You have to
think about the right questions to
ask. You know, like your kid ask you for
some chocolate and you say, "Oh,
chocolate." You know, is it yummy? Yes.
You know, is it like great to hide in
your school bag and eat during class?
Yeah. Man, is it fun to go to the
dentist? And he's like, "No, you know,
do you like the drill thing?" I mean,
you
know, and he's like, "No, Dad. I don't
like that." You know, okay, but you sure
you want the chocolate? You know, and
then you don't tell the kid, "Oh, it's
going to give you cavities, you know.
don't eat chocolate. You know, you let
him go to the dentist in his mind and go
to the drill in his mind and then he
says, "Dad, you know what?" And you can
have the chocolate. That's what dad
wanted all along.
[Music]
Anyway, okay. Uh, now Q&A. We have We
have 10 minutes and then we're ready to
do the we're ready to do the nine
questions. How many answers?
That's up to you. That's up to you. And
I think it's a beautiful way to end
seven years of negative. Okay. All
right. And by the way, any questions?
Okay. If you want to ask a question
about your neighbor's dog, I don't mind.
I have one. I haven't figured it out.
Check. Check. Check. Oh, okay.
I was just wondering since yoga was
developed to help with our
meditation in the five houses, will yoga
be in the house of meditation or which
house will that be kind of taught in for
us to help the students of that house?
Yeah, it's a great question. Um
so we have this new idea of five houses
of ACI and it's kind of uh ACI is so
uh
it's so massive it's includes so many
things that it has become ridiculous to
become an ACI master. the seven years of
the foundation courses, seven years of
the diamond weight courses, 14 years of
the alarm room courses, 28 years of
study just to say I took the courses,
okay? Much less be a master. So what we
decided is to split into specialties
like PhD specialties. So I don't try to
and it was inspired by my trip to
Princeton back to Princeton and watching
all the beautiful uh departments and and
you know people said what's your
department Gisha and I took them to 1879
hall you know and I told stories we sat
we stood under the tree where where the
Indian boy sat and talked me into going
to India and uh it was very beautiful.
So anyway, um it's too it'd be too much
at Princeton to take a PhD in
everything. It's crazy. It's insane.
It's too much stuff. And ACI has become
too much stuff. And I don't know if you
feel it, but I feel it. I feel it
because I feel people going, "Ah 12,
15, they're their fingers look like AI
fingers, you know."
So we decided to specialize we decided
to have departments and it's called the
five houses and uh they are first house
is classics house that's traditional AI
ACI found ACI ACI foundation courses
then
what's the second one Samari house yeah
and that's that's under taught in in
ACI. Okay. Frankly, and we're on we are
developing 101 or 100
101 I'm filming 100 medit 101
meditations that I was taught in my
life. I think we're up to nine or 10
something like that and I try to do it
once a week. So that's samadei house.
Then oh and then there'll be a secular
side which teaches meditation at Google.
Okay. In a non Buddhist way. Then third
house.
Oh mountain house. Yeah. Which is
basically go to diamond mountain and sit
in a cabin and do retreats. Learn how to
do retreats.
And after five h five house world
fundraiser where grandpa put in
$25,000 and I don't know I haven't seen
the numbers today but I'm sure you guys
have matched
me
minimum. Nobody's jumping up and
down. Huh? You did. You did.
Oh, well anyway,
uh I hope you can match me. I put in 25
with the help of the Russians. Okay. And
you're going to if you want to match me,
match me. But that's to teach normal
people. Uh you know, retreat, then
fourth
house, staircase house, lam rim house,
then fifth house, diamond house. The
question is where do you put yoga? I I
uh we had an organization called
YSI 20 years ago. It died. The director
quit, the staff quit. You know, I was
too busy. And um so it died. Then uh I
don't know like five years ago, Carney
came to me and said, "Can I serve you
llama? Do you need anything?" I said,
"Resurrect that dead body called YSI."
like go to the graveyard, open up the
box, pull YSI out. You know, there's uh
many courses. There's 12 courses, I
think, something
12 sections. There's hundreds of pages
of translation and homeworks. And she
said, "Yes, sir. I will uh res resurrect
YSI." And she did it. And so, I kind of
leave that to YSI. there there's some
things that are being done so well that
I don't think ACI has to do you know so
I I don't think ACI we will have we will
always have yoga DCI has yoga
uh you know but I would like
to when I have a DCI yoga program or we
have a ACI yoga program I would like to
call YSI who's they are experts like
this lady I suspect she's a YSI like
person I don't know for
sure but uh that's all they're so good
at it they specialized in it that I feel
like we should leave it to them it's a
huge topic it it takes
u it would take uh four or five years to
get through it and I think it's too much
to add to another house okay I think but
I think every house should do yoga okay
to stay
healthy
Okay. Good
morning, when I was in Kyoto at CFP
course, when I first heard you talking
about Fraini on the stage, I had a very
strong feeling. And in China, I am doing
a training for females. And after I feel
Yeah, I have this question. Okay,
venerable GLA, thank you so much. Uh
when I first heard uh you taught me in
Coyoto uh last December, I heard uh
first time I heard about the Guini world
and because I was doing a business focus
on training the ladies entrepreneurs.
Yeah. Okay.
Okay. So, uh after hearing that I was uh
uh preparing for that. So, Ga I want to
ask you if I want to reach uh Vajaya
Yogini's world in business. I want to
build this Vajay Yugini's world in
reality. So uh vener vener teacher
what's your most important suggestion
for me? Yeah thank you. Great question.
It's a great question and I will say the
guardian is emptiness. My answer is the
garden is empty.
[Laughter]
So, uh, anyways,
uh, when you're on the airplane and the
lady next to you is irritating you, or
if, by the way, if you're a lady, it's a
fat man. Okay, I'm talking to guy, okay?
in uh when they irritate you. If you
think about they are
empty, you know, and you can even do
this when they really irritate you, you
can go,
[Music]
you know, you can do this mudra on the
plane. You know, you can do it on the
plane. And then the next natural
step as we did it already is to believe
they came from
central
casting. Okay, they are just an actor
uh who came from the main office where
they assign actors. Okay, so that's
diamond ring. That's tantra. That's
tantra. That's tantra. Okay. Emptiness
leads to tantra. And and you can do it
on the plane. You don't have to do a
fire offering. You'll get in trouble on
the
plane. You don't have to do all that
stuff. Okay. So, here's how it goes.
Irritation, then
blame, you know, and then catch
yourself.
self-awareness and then
emptiness and then how many things not
coming from
me. Therefore, this lady must be special
and she must be she came from central
casting
because Arya would not stay in this
world for 2,000
years. Grandparents teach it to their
grandchildren for 2,000 years. 100
generations. It wouldn't happen if it
didn't work for somebody. People don't
pass on things that don't work. People
pass on things that work. So if it
survived up to now, 2,000 years to this
day, to this room, ending
today, if it survived up to now, it must
have worked for somebody. And then those
people must be
Buddha got it and that's diamond way to
think like that is diamond way. So just
work on the gardina and by the way he's
the first great diamond ray teacher
after n buddhura he if you check the
books written by narajuna I can teach
you more tantric books by naruna than
non- tantric books by naruna
and his uh ceremony for the bodhic safa
vows is found in the tantras
[Music]
Okay. All right. Yay. Yes, sir.